[Music]
to finish this whole course I'd like
to begin as I'd like to finish where we
started when we first met I stood on a
chair said hello and then started
cutting a movie strip
remember so I'd like to show you two
demos you've cut many of you have done
the project even you've seen cutting a
movie strip but a single movie
strip here I have brought two ordinary
strips so they're not Twisted which I
glued at 90° to each
other is that clear
let's cut each of these strips along the
center
line what do you think
happens in order to think
clearly focus
on the part of the
picture which is at the Crossing of the
two sheets okay and please imagine that
that direction goes in the back connects
without a Twist and this direction comes
in front and connect twist well cutting
means that I take
scissors pink scissors and then cut it
along here and then cut it along here so
in the middle I cut in a cross what's
going to happen well if I start going
here I come there right where do I
reappear here right not here here
because because it's not twisted and
then I go there and then I come out from
here the are you old enough to have
played something called
Pacman or is that prehistory for you but
anyway so this goes out and then appears
here and then disappears here and then I
come back here so how many pieces do we
get one piece so let's see what we get
do you have a guess we know that we are
going to get one piece because we are
good sign
this but let's see what kind of piece we
get two ordinary twists uh ordinary
strips
untwisted glued perpendicularly to each
other yeah I'm now
cutting one of the components one of the
strips along the center line in order to
increase the drama I shall start cutting
the other one without finishing the
first
yeah I'm
doing okay now I'm about to do this
Central cut I've cut almost here almost
here almost here almost here all right
are you ready everyone awake if you have
been asleep and I understand because
some people have been partying too much
um it's time to wake up so I've cut the
first piece and
then I cut this
and I cut this have you have have you
had a
guess is this more less what you
expected so
far and
then I finish
cutting and I
get perfect
square you know you are you allowed to
applaud
[Applause]
what shall we do
next we can exactly we can glue two
movie strips together who said that who
said that who said
thatuh so can and has a sense of
research so um let's glue two movie
strips together like so I brought
already
one this time I mean you can do many
other things for example you can have
an audence strip together with a movie
strip yeah that's one possibility or in
fact you can do two things in this case
in case you want to try later and I hope
you will try later I like to point out a
very important feature those two movie
strips are opposite movie strips I hope
it's clear what I mean you know one of
the movie
scks looks like this
the other strip
looks like this do you see the
difference the twist directions are
different one strip I twisted like this
the other strip I twisted like this and
then I glue them
together we shall not do the more
obvious one where you have two movie
strips of the same twist same
orientation if you like so same same
chirality and glue them along um
perpendicular to each other okay let's
do this but for that when we finish it's
going to be a little in tangle so we
have to desend tangle and for that I
need an assistant so please Adrian come
forward and when we finish cutting this
I'm going to just hold one of the pieces
like this and show show it to people and
then I'll try to do the reement that why
we standing there
okay are you ready we have our guest and
what we shall see is uh turns out to be
a message from me to the aim students
past present this class and
future and that will be a fitting point
at which to stop again I cut along one
of the movie
strips along the center line by the way
all Center Line I keep cutting I keep
cutting I keep cutting along the center
line
okay let's cut that Adrian can tell you
that I'm not cheating
yet I'm cutting Center Line yes yes yes
good good Adrian is a very honest man
and we can trust him and I keep cutting
along the center line along the center
line along the center line I keep
cutting along the center line and I have
now almost finished so if you think of
this picture but this time with
twists I cut almost here almost to the
center almost to the center so I'm now
about to finish cutting the central
cross and this I shall do
now poof
ready
poof how many pieces P do we
get
huh one two who thinks we get one
piece who thinks we get two pieces who
thinks we get three pieces
four who thinks we get zero
pieces first we get two pieces but now
please uh hold hold up your hands and
hold them like this and hold them like
this
turn and then turn this
[Music]
way so I think it would be nice to put
this up somewhere on the wall and that's
the end of my course I hope you'll have
a great
[Applause]
carer